<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> – Platforms</title>
    <link>https://docs.ondat.io/v2.5/docs/platforms/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Platforms on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    
	  <atom:link href="https://docs.ondat.io/v2.5/docs/platforms/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      
        
      
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: Google GKE</title>
      <link>https://docs.ondat.io/v2.5/docs/platforms/google-gke/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://docs.ondat.io/v2.5/docs/platforms/google-gke/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;StorageOS is fully compatible with GKE when using the Ubuntu images. To
install StorageOS on Google GKE, follow our Kubernetes &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.ondat.io/v2.5/docs/install/kubernetes&#34;&gt;installation instructions&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For StorageOS to work normally it is &lt;strong&gt;required to use the Ubuntu images&lt;/strong&gt; for
the Google GKE node pools. The default container image does not fulfil the system
requirements because of the lack of the TCMU kernel modules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more details about the OS Distributions check the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.ondat.io/v2.5/docs/prerequisites/systemconfiguration&#34;&gt;System Configuration&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;google-anthos&#34;&gt;Google Anthos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ondat is compatible with Google Anthos. However it is required that the
Linux image distribution used fulfils the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.ondat.io/v2.5/docs/prerequisites/systemconfiguration&#34;&gt;System Configuration&lt;/a&gt; prerequisites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once a Kubernetes cluster is provisioned, StorageOS can be installed following
the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.ondat.io/v2.5/docs/install/kubernetes&#34;&gt;instructions&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: OpenShift</title>
      <link>https://docs.ondat.io/v2.5/docs/platforms/openshift/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://docs.ondat.io/v2.5/docs/platforms/openshift/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;Ondat V2 supports Openshift v4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red Hat OpenShift and Ondat communicate with each other to perform actions such as
creation, deletion and mounting of volumes through CSI. The CSI container
running in the Ondat Daemonset creates a Linux socket that allows the
communication between Red Hat OpenShift and Ondat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;installation&#34;&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ondat v2 supports Red Hat OpenShift 4.0, 4.1, 4.2, 4.3, 4.4 and 4.5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To install Ondat on Red Hat OpenShift, follow our &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.ondat.io/v2.5/docs/install/openshift&#34;&gt;installation instructions&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⚠️ Red Hat Openshift 4 uses the CRI-O container runtime that sets a default PID
limit of 1024. Ondat recommends that the limit be raised to 32768.
Please see our &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.ondat.io/v2.5/docs/prerequisites/pidlimits&#34;&gt;prerequisites&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;red-hat-openshift-upgrades&#34;&gt;Red Hat OpenShift Upgrades&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red Hat OpenShift provides an upgrade operator that automates the process of
orchestrator version changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This procedure can cause Ondat to malfunction due to sequential node
restarts not taking the presence of stateful application data into
consideration. To avoid this issue, make sure all stateful workloads using
Ondat Volumes are stopped - usually by scaling StatefulSets to 0. Please
contact Ondat support for further advice if required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;⚠️ Red Hat OpenShift requires the internal registry to be available during the upgrade,
however Ondat volumes may not be available. Therefore using Ondat
for the internal registry is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;csi-container-storage-interface-note&#34;&gt;CSI (Container Storage Interface) Note&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CSI is the standard that enables storage drivers to release on their own
schedule. This allows storage vendors to upgrade, update, and enhance their
drivers without the need to update Kubernetes source code, or follow Kubernetes
release cycles. Ondat v2 uses CSI to implement communication with the
Red Hat OpenShift controlplane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ondat-persistentvolumeclaims&#34;&gt;Ondat PersistentVolumeClaims&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The user can provide standard PVC definitions and Ondat will dynamically
provision them. Ondat presents volumes to containers with standard POSIX
mount targets. This enables the Kubelet to mount Ondat volumes using
standard linux device files. Checkout &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.ondat.io/v2.5/docs/prerequisites/systemconfiguration&#34;&gt;device presentation&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: Rancher</title>
      <link>https://docs.ondat.io/v2.5/docs/platforms/rancher/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://docs.ondat.io/v2.5/docs/platforms/rancher/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;To install Ondat on Rancher, follow our &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.ondat.io/v2.5/docs/install/rancher&#34;&gt;installation instructions&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ondat transparently supports Rancher deployments using CentOS, RHEL or
Debian and can support other Linux distributions detailed in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.ondat.io/v2.5/docs/prerequisites/systemconfiguration&#34;&gt;systems supported page&lt;/a&gt; if the
appropriate kernel modules are present.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
